Finding Aid for the Pearl Radcliffe Lindal Papers, 1938-1947
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Pearl Radcliffe Lindal Papers, 1938-1947
Mus. Arc. 43
Lindal, Pearl Radcliffe
2 boxes ( 73 folders )
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Collection consists of 1 scrapbook of clippings about Pearl Radcliffe Lindal's career as a songwriter and eleven of her songs as published in collections. Material inserted into the scrapbook includes correspondence and additional prose writings by Lindal.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ida Mae Hussey, 2008.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
Pearl Radcliffe Lindal was born April 22 1889 to Elizabeth Higson. She was a composer and music teacher in the Buffalo, New York area. She was elected to serve as pianist of the local Waldensian Society probably around 1940. She began to write cowboy songs sometime in the 1930s and secured a contract from American Music Publishing for at least eight songs. She married Lewis Lindal, an attorney in Buffalo. Presumably after his death she remarried, becoming the wife of Richard R. Lennartz. She died November 25 1966 in Buffalo. The obituary in the November 26 1966 Buffalo News noted that she had been a life member of the Osseo Chapter Number 386, Order of the Eastern Star. She was buried in the Lancaster Rural Cemetery (Lancaster, New York).
Scope and Content Note
The collection as received consisted of a scrapbook of clippings and letters regarding Pearl Radcliffe Lindal's career as a songwriter. There were only seven leaves of the scrapbook with content attached to pages; the rest of the material was loosely inserted. The contents of the scrapbook were removed from the scrapbook after the original organization was photocopied. Contents were then organized into series as stated in the Arrangement section. The collection also includes eleven of Lindal's songs, ten of which are contained within published song collections.
The writings in the collection are a mix of poems and short tales or aphorisms.
Arrangement
I. Writings
II. Correspondence
III. Programs and bulletins
IV. Clippings
V. Scrapbook copies
VI. Songs
Container List
- Writings, 1938-1947, I.; Folder 1-30
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Are you lonesome Mr. Moon, August 24 1938, 1 manuscript leaf (Box 1, Item 1)
  - Children's day, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 2)
  - Come unto me, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 3)
  - Coronation, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 4)
  - Danny Cupid, February 18 1947, 1 manuscript leaf; On verso: Lindal's Are you lonesome Mr. Moon (Box 1, Item 5)
  - A day in the woods, undated, 2 typescript leaves (Box 1, Item 6)
  - Dusty road, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 7)
  - An early morning walk, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 8)
  - Evening on the prairie, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 9)
  - The family picnic day, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 10)
  - Grieve not beloved (To a friend), undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 11)
  - Little white house, August 14 1939, 4 typescript leaves; Four typed copies. Two copies are dated; one copy has pencil manuscript verses on verso. (Box 1, Item 12)
  - Making use of odd moments, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 13)
  - The master's hand, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 14)
  - My dog, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 15)
  - My dream, undated, 1 manuscript leaf (Box 1, Item 16)
  - My part time gardener, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 17)
  - My song to you, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 18)
  - An old lady, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 19)
  - People I like, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 20)
  - People who win, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 21)
  - Presto, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 22)
  - Resting, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 23)
  - Should children be reasoned with or spanked, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 24)
  - Spring sonnet, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 25)
  - Things I love, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 26)
  - The traveling ant, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 27)
  - Wanted... A song, a lovely song, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 28)
  - Where the stars peek-a-boo, May 22 1939, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Item 29)
  - Where Western skies are shining, June 7 1939, 1 manuscript leaf (Box 1, Item 30)
- Correspondence, 1939-1941, II.; Folder 31-47
  Folders arranged in alphabetical order by correspondent. Some folders include responses from Lindal.
  - Bossard, Belle R.: Correspondence to Pearl Lindal, August 30 1939, 1 signed card (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Bingel, Mrs. D.: Correspondence to Pearl Lindal, July 23 1939, 1 signed card (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Boyd, Bill, 1910-1977: Correspondence to Pearl Lindal, July 29 1939, January 11 1940, 2 signed typescript leaves (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Letterhead: Bill Boyd and His Cowboy Ramblers. Also includes a flyer with complete list of recordings by Bill Boyd and His Cowboy Ramblers.
  - Crummet, Evelyn: Correspondence to and from Pearl Lindal, July 23 1939, July 26 1939, September 4 1939, 2 typescript leaves from Crummet, 1 typescript leaf from Lindal (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Fitts, Ada M., 1869-: Correspondence to Pearl Lindal, August 16 1939, 2 manuscript leaves (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Flower Grower: Correspondence to Pearl Lindal, February 12 1941, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Green, John F. C. (Frederick Carl), b. 1892: Correspondence to Pearl Lindal, July 21 1940, 1 manuscript leaf; Letterhead: Evangelical Congregational Church, McKeesport, Pennsylvania. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Lenkow, Jennie M.: Correspondence to Pearl Lindal, July 22 1939, 1 manuscript leaf; Letterhead: Lebanon Shrine No. 3, Buffalo, New York. (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - McMichael, C. H. (Henry): Correspondence to and from Pearl Lindal, July 20 1939, July 22 1939, 2 typescript leaves (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Mitchell, Edna E. July 21 1939, 1 business card with envelope (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Myers, Mary: Correspondence to and from Pearl Lindal, August 2 1939, August 12 1939, 1 manuscript leaf, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Nelson, Margaret: Correspondence to Pearl Lindal, undated, 1 manuscript leaf; Letterhead: Avon House Publishers, New York. (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Reiman, Theodore F.: Correspondence to and from Pearl Lindal, July 20 1939, July 22 1939, August 15 1939, 2 typescript leaves from Reiman, 1 typescript leaf from Lindal (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Russell, Richard: Correspondence to and from Pearl Lindal, July 20 1939, July 22 1939, 2 typescript leaves (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - S., A. W.: Mail to Pearl Lindal, September 25 1940, 1 printed folded leaf; Flyer about painting of Charles M. Russell. (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Thomson, L. H.: Correspondence to Pearl Lindal, August 6 1940, 1 envelope; Actual correspondence is missing, only the envelope remains. (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Wurtz, Olive U. S.: Correspondence to Pearl Lindal, undated, 1 manuscript leaf (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Programs and bulletins, 1939-1944, III.; Folder 48-51
  Folders arranged in alphabetical order by organization.
  - American Music Inc.: Bulletin, June 1944, 3 typescript leaves; Lindal songs are listed under two sections in the bulletin: Songs featured on the radio, and Cross section of Radio Logging. (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - National League of American Pen Women. Western New York Branch: Concert program featuring June Hards, violin, Kenneth Gill, tenor, and Walter Peek, piano, undated, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - St. Stephen's Episcopal Church (Buffalo, New York): Concert program, October 24 1939, 1 printed leaf (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Zorah Berry Concert Management: Flyer for concert season, 1939-1940, 1 printed leaf (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Clippings, 1939-1940, IV.; Folder 52-61
  Folders arranged in chronological order. Undated items arranged alphabetically by caption of article. Folders 60-61 are oversized and are housed in Box 2.
  - Local woman author of several new songs, August 3 1939, 1 printed leaf; Source: Walden-Bailey-Genesee News (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Altar Guild to hold silver tea, October 1939, 1 scrapbook leaf with 3 newspaper clippings; Source: Unknown. (Box 1, Folder 53)
    Three clippings: Song writer is 77 (about Carrie Jacobs Bond); Altar Guild to hold silver tea (refers to program in Folder 50); Guild holds musical.
  - Radio dispute brings arrest of Gene Buck, February 23 1940, 1 printed leaf; Source: Unknown. (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - A little greenhouse for $94.61, undated, 4 printed pages; Source: Unknown magazine, possibly Flower Grower. (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Buffalo woman writes cowboy songs though she never went West, undated, 1 printed leaf; Source: Unknown. (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Hold annual rally: Rev. Seymour traces Waldensian history, undated, 1 printed leaf; Source: Unknown. Manuscript note indicates Pearl Lindal was elected pianist for the Waldensian Society at this meeting. (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Popular songwriter sees opportunities, undated, 1 printed leaf; Source: Unknown. Reprinted from article originally published in Portland Oregon News-Telegram November 25 1932. (Box 1, Folder 58)
    Article about songwriter Sylvester Cross.
  - Stockton boyhood theme of song written by wife, undated, 1 printed leaf; Source: Fredonia Censor. (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Local woman writes cowboy songs and she's never seen a cowpuncher, July 20 1939, 1 printed leaf; Source: Buffalo Evening News. (Box 2, Folder 60)
    Attached to scrapbook leaf with additional manuscript marginalia.
  - Full house enjoys musicale at St. Stephen's: Western songs composed by guild president on program, November 2 1939, 1 printed leaf; Source: Walden-Bailey-Genesee News (Box 2, Folder 61)
    Attached to scrapbook leaf that also holds the concert program for the event.
- Scrapbook copies, 1939, V.; Folder 62
  Photocopied leaves (seven) in order as originally received in scrapbook.
  - Original scrapbook binder with photocopies of leaves as received, 1939, 7 photocopied leaves; Does not include all the materials that had been loosely inserted into the scrapbook. (Box 2, Folder 62)
- Songs, 1938-1941, VI.; Folder 63-73
  Folders arranged in alphabetical order by title of Lindal song within collection.
  - Church out on the plain, 1939, Words and music by Pearl R. Lindal, Ann Luger, and J. L. Mitchell; Published in "Dude" Martin's folio of original songs of the plains. Portland, Ore.: American Music, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - He’s sleeping tonight by the trail, 1939, Words and music by Carrie P. Kirby, Pearl R. Lindal, and Helen C. Olson; Published in Jerry Smith's folio of original home and range songs. No. 1.. Portland, Ore.: American Music, 1939 (Box 2, Item 64)
  - In old Virginia, 1941, Words and music by Ethyl Isabel De Planque, Pearl R. Lindal, and Florence L. Yarwood; Published in Home and hill country ballads. Folio no. 4. Portland, Ore.: American Music, 1941 (Box 2, Item 65)
  - Mammy's little honey chile, 1941, Words and music by Modena Gage, Pearl R. Lindal, and Hulda M. McCollom; Published in Home and hill country ballads. Folio no. 6. Portland, Ore.: American Music, 1941 (Box 2, Item 66)
  - My boyhood home, 1938, Words and music by Pearl Radcliffe Lindal; Published in Album of new radio favorites, containing twenty beautiful new songs. Portland, Ore.: American Music, 1938 (Box 2, Item 67)
  - Prairie lullaby, 1939, Words and music by Pearl R. Lindal, C. Henry Wilkerson, and Bill Boyd; Published in Bill Boyd and his Cowboy Ramblers' folio of western songs, no. 1: containing 20 original songs complete with words and music, guitar, ukulele and banjo chords. Portland, Ore.: American Music, 1939 (Box 2, Item 68)
  - Prairie rose, 1940, Words and music by Thomas J. Byrnes,, Pearl R. Lindal, and Joseph Dobbs; Published in Cowboy ballads: containing 20 new songs, complete with words & music, guitar, ukulele & banjo chords. Portland, Ore.: American Music, 1940 (Box 2, Item 69)
  - Sweet Ida mine, 1941, Words and music by James Grant Alcorn, Henry J. Sommers, and Pearl Lindal; Published in Home and hill country ballads. Folio no. 5. Portland, Ore.: American Music, 1941 (Box 2, Item 70)
  - Swingtime symphony, undated, By Pearl Radcliffe Lindal; 1 songsheet (Box 2, Item 71)
  - Under the Western sky, 1939, Words and music by Pearl R. Lindal and Robert M. Burney; Published in Golden West Cowboys' folio of songs of the golden West. No. 1.. Portland, Ore.: American Music, 1939 (Box 2, Item 72)
  - When it's honeysuckle time in Caroline, 1941, Words and music by Pearl R. Lindal, Hulda M. McCollom, and Gertrude I. MacLeod; Published in Heart ballads, folio no. 8. Portland, Ore.: American Music, 1941 (Box 2, Item 73)
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Subjects
Cowboys--West (U.S.)--Songs and music; Songs, American; Songs with piano; Composers--New York (State)--Buffalo; Women composers--New York (State)--Buffalo
Genres
Songs (document genre); Scores; Scrapbooks; Clippings (information artifacts)